Martin Skarzynski Laptev

240-595-3460 maptv@engineer.com maptv.github.io maptv maptv

Cloud Computing Data Science Machine Learning Technical Management Software Engineering Solution Architecture

Mission

My goal is to lead the next generation of scientists and engineers in building solutions that integrate substantive expertise from diverse fields with machine intelligence. Through my work, I strive to promote open source software, such as the Quarto publishing system, which I use to build dashboards, presentations, reports, websites, and other digital deliverables. Overall, I aim to leverage my broad scientific background and technical expertise to help transform the promises of science and technology into a better future for all of humanity.

Recent Experience

Lead Instructor, General Assembly

July 2019 - Present

- Teaches various courses such as:
 - Data Analytics
 - Front-End Web Development
 - Tech Excellence Data Science
 - Python Programming
 - React Development

Lead Instructor, **Data Society**

October 2019 - Present

- Teaches workshops such as:
 - Machine Learning
 - Data Science Bootcamp
 - Natural Language Processing
 - Deep Learning
 - Data Science Academy
 - Python Programming
 - DevOps
 - Data Visualization
 - R Programming

Vice President, **Data Community DC**

April 2022 - Present

• Leads a nonprofit organization that supports eleven Meetup groups

Adjunct Professor, Virginia Tech

September 2021 - December 2023

- Taught two graduate courses for the Computer Science and Statistics Departments:
 - Machine Learning
 - Data Analytics

- Provided customers with scientific and technical expertise in:
 - Computer Vision
 - Data Architecture
 - Data Visualization
 - Genomics
 - Machine Learning
 - Real World Evidence
- Built Artificial Intelligence (AI) solutions and Machine Learning Operations (MLOps) systems using:
 - Amazon SageMaker
 - AWS Developer Tools
 - AWS Lambda
 - Amazon EventBridge
 - AWS CloudFormation
 - AWS IAM
 - Amazon EMR
 - AWS Databases
 - AWS Service Catalog
- Obtained 3 AWS certification
 - Solutions Architect Associate
 - Cloud Practitioner
 - Practical Data Science

AI Engineering Manager, **Booz Allen Hamilton**

October 2019 - March 2022

- Led a team of data scientists and software developers working on a cyber intelligence application
- Spearheaded interdisciplinary COVID19 <u>visualization</u>, <u>genomics</u>, and statistical modeling efforts
- Obtained the *Microsoft Azure Data Scientist Associate* certification

Adjunct Professor, George Washington University

September 2021 - December 2023

- Taught two undergraduate courses for the Women's Leadership Program:
 - Biology of Organisms
 - Women and Leadership

Biomedical Scientist, National Institutes of Health

June 2009 - April 2021

- Integrated clinical, laboratory, epidemiologic, genomic, and medical imaging data
- Combined deep learning and statistical inference using stacked ensembles
- Conducted genomic analysis of immune and cancer cells
- Developed and tested pharmaceutical and immunotherapeutic agents
- Quantified cancer cell signaling pathways
- Mentored trainees from four different NIH training programs:
 - Summer Internship Program
 - Medical Research Scholars Program
 - NIH HiSTEP
 - Biomedical Research Training Program for Individuals from Underrepresented Groups

- Coadministered an academic program with over twenty faculty members
- Taught three graduate data science courses:
 - Introduction to Python
 - Introduction to Text Mining
 - Applied Machine Learning
- Taught nine graduate biotechnology workshops:
 - Pharmacometric Analyses using R
 - Cellular Immunology
 - Research Tools for Studying Disease
 - Junior Scientist Training Program
 - Recombinant DNA Methodology
 - Genetics Institute
 - Immunochemistry and Antibodies
 - Cancer Prevention
 - Flow Cytometry

Select Publications

JAMA Netw Open, [] a deep learning model [] to inform lung cancer screening intervals	March 2023
Glob Health Epidemiol Genom, SARS-CoV-2 genome-based severity predictions correspond to [] higher viral load February 2023	
Virological, Linking genotype to phenotype [] in SARS-CoV-2 []	April 2022
Evol Med Public Health, <u>Variants in SARS-CoV-2 associated with mild or severe outcome</u>	June 2021
J Natl Cancer Inst, Using prediction models to reduce [] disparities in [] lung cancer screening [] January 2021	
Clin Cancer Res, Interactions between ibrutinib and anti-CD20 antibodies []	January 2016
Bioconjug Chem, Designing the furin-cleavable linker in recombinant immunotoxins []	May 2015
Front Public Health, Health disparities in the immunoprevention of [HPV] [] associated malignancies December 2015	
Blood, Pathogenic role of [BCR] signaling and canonical NF-κB activation in [MCL]	July 2016
Cancer Res, Harnessing the Fcµ receptor for [] therapy of [CLL]	October 2014
Education	
MPH, Epidemiology and Biostatistics	May 2018
PhD, Tumor Biology	May 2015
MS, Biotechnology	June 2009
BA, Biology	May 2007
Select Awards	
Community Contribution of the Year Category Finalist, AWS Builder Awards	February 2023
Artificial Intelligence Solutions Architect Award, BAH Emergent Skills Program	January 2022
TransFellowship Research Award, Cancer Prevention Fellowship Program	June 2019
Fellows Award for Research Excellence, National Institutes of Health	June 2015
Orloff Science Award, National Heart, Lung, Blood Institute	October 2014
Director's Science Award, National Heart, Lung, Blood Institute	January 2014